

mhepaixao.github.io/homepage

#### About Me\_

I currently work as a Visiting Scholar at the State University of Ceara (UECE). At UECE, I supervise Master's and PhD students, teach modules targeted at Grad students and act as a software engineer on R&D projects in collaboration with industry partners. I received my PhD degree from University College London, where I was supervised by Prof. Mark Harman and Dr Jens Krinke.

My research interests tend to revolve around software and repositories analysis. I find software engineering data fascinating due to its complexity, lack of structure and mix of technical and social aspects. My recent publications involve microservices, software architecture, software refactoring, modern code review, and mining software repositories. Search-based software engineering has been my introduction to academia and it is a topic I cannot keep myself away from.

# Formal Education

**University College London** London, UK

PHD IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Oct. 2014 - Aug. 2018

Thesis: Software Restructuring: Understanding Longitudinal Architectural Changes and Refactoring

**State University of Ceara** Fortaleza, Brazil

MASTER'S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Feb. 2012 - Jul. 2014

Dissertation: A Robust Optimisation Approach to the Next Release Problem

Federal Institute of Education in Science and Technology

Fortaleza, Brazil **BACHELOR IN TELEMATICS** Feb. 2009 - Nov. 2011

# **Work Experience**

**State University of Ceara** Fortaleza, Brazil

VISITING SCHOLAR Jan. 2021 - PRESENT

- Part of the research and teaching staff of the PhD programme in computer science
- Supervises a mixed group of Master's and undergraduate students
- · Teaches Grad modules on Mining Software Repositories, Tools, Continuous Integration, Automation and DevOps
- Software engineer (tech leader) in R&D projects with industry collaborators

**University of Fortaleza** Fortaleza, Brazil

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

Oct. 2019 - Dec. 2020

- Part of the Lab. of Data Science and Artificial Intelligence
- Coordinated R&D projects involving industrial partners and government bodies
- · Supervised Master's and PhD candidates on the topics of Software Engineering, Program Analysis and Software Biases

**State University of Ceara** Fortaleza, Brazil RESEARCH ASSISTANT Sep. 2018 - Sep. 2019

• Part of the research and teaching staff of the Master's programme in computer science

- · Taught Master's modules on Mining Software Repositories, Tools, Environments, Automation and DevOps
- Supervised a mixed group of Master's and undergraduate students

**University College London** London, UK

Oct. 2014 - Ago. 2018

Feb. 2012 - Jul. 2014

PHD CANDIDATE

- Thesis involved software architecture, software refactoring and mining software repositories
- Member of the CREST Centre
- · Program Manager of the CREST Open Workshops

**State University of Ceara** Fortaleza, Brazil

- Dissertation involved search-based software engineering and software requirements
- · Member of the GOES research group

MASTER'S STUDENT

# **Teaching Experience**

#### **DevOps, Tools and Automation**

State University of Ceara

Lecturer 2019 - PRESENT

This is a course I created as part of my teaching activities as a visiting scholar at UECE. This course is targeted at Grad students in software engineering. During the course, the students are exposed to DevOps concepts, ranging from social to technical aspects. In addition, I teach and discuss the main activities in the software development lifecycle that are commonly automated. Finally, I present a set of state-of-practice and state-of-the-art tools to assist in automation.

## **Mining Software Repositories**

State University of Ceara

LECTURER

2019 - PRESENT

This is a course I created as part of my teaching activities as a visiting scholar at UECE. This is a research-intensive course targeted at Grad students in software engineering. During the course, the students are exposed to a wide range of MSR-related topics, ranging from the basic building blocks of MSR research to the step-by-step process of conducting a MSR research project to presentations of recently published state-of-the-art papers.

Tools and Environments

University College London

TEACHING ASSISTANT 2017

This course was targeted at Bachelor's and Master's students in software engineering at UCL, in which the students were exposed to several tools to automate the software development process. I was responsible for the tools' lab demonstrations.

## **Software Systems Integration**

University College London

TEACHING ASSISTANT 201

This course was targeted at Bachelor's and Master's students in software engineering at UCL, in which the students were expected to develop a software system to a real-world external client. I was responsible to supervise two groups of students in all phases of the products' lifecycle. Both groups I supervised developed machine learning powered mobile apps for Microsoft UK.

# **Software Requirements and Architecture**

University College London

Teaching Assistant 2016

This course was targeted at Bachelor's and Master's students in software engineering at UCL, in which the students were expected to elicit the requirements and design the architecture of a software system to be developed to a real-world external client. I was responsible to supervise the students in requirements elicitation and architecture design techniques. Both groups I supervised worked with clients from Microsoft UK.

# **Serving the Community**

I included below a selected set of venues that I serve as editor or reviewer. For the full list of venues, please refer to my homepage (mhepaixao.github.io/homepage/)

#### **Editorial**

I serve as an **Associate Editor** of the Journal of Software Engineering Research and Development (JSERD), which is the prime journal publication of software engineering research in Brazil.

# Journals

I SERVE AS A REVIEWER OF THE FOLLOWING JOURNALS:

- IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering
- Empirical Software Engineering
- ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology
- Journal of Systems and Software

#### Conferences

I HAVE SERVED (OR WILL SERVE) AS PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER AND/OR REVIEWER OF THE FOLLOWING CONFERENCES:

- 44th International Conference on Software Engineering 2022 (SEIP PC Member)
- 18th International Conference on Mining Software Repositories 2021 (PC Member)
- 29th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Program Comprehension 2021 (PC Member)
- 28th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Program Comprehension 2020 (PC Member)
- 27th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Program Comprehension 2019 (PC Member)
- Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference 2018 (SBSE PC Member)

# Full List of Publications Assessing Exception Handling Testing Practices in Open-Source Libraries (EMSE) Luan Lima, Lincoln Rocha, Carla Bezerra, Matheus Paixao 2021 **Empirical Software Engineering** Behind the Intents: An In-depth Empirical Study on Software Refactoring in Modern Code Review (MSR'20) Matheus Paixao, Anderson Uchôa, Ana Carla Bibiano, Daniel Oliveira, Alessandro Garcia, Jens Krinke, Emilio 2020 ARVONIO Working Conference on Mining Software Repositories Does Code Review Really Remove Coding Convention Violations? (SCAM'20) DongGyun Han, Chaiyong Ragkhitwetsagul, Jens Krinke, Matheus Paixao, Giovanni Rosa 2020 Source Code Analysis and Manipulation MDE in the Wild: An Exploratory Analysis on What Developers are Discussing on Q&A Platforms (SBES'20) Carlos Alberto Medeiros, Alan Bandeira, Paulo Henrique Maia, Matheus Paixao 2020 Brazilian Symposium on Software Engineering Using Stack Overflow to Assess Technical Debt Identification on Software Projects (SBES'20) ELIAKIM GAMA, SÁVIO FREIRE, MANOEL MENDONÇA, RODRIGO O. SPÍNOLA, MATHEUS PAIXAO, MARIELA I. CORTÉS 2020 Brazilian Symposium on Software Engineering The Impact of Code Review on Architectural Changes (TSE) MATHEUS PAIXAO, JENS KRINKE, DONGGYUN HAN, CHAIYONG RAGKHITWETSAGUL, MARK HARMAN 2019 IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering Toxic code snippets on Stack Overflow (TSE) Chaiyong Ragkhitwetsagul, Jens Krinke, Matheus Paixao, Giuseppe Bianco, Rocco Oliveto 2019 IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering We Need to Talk about Microservices: an Analysis from the Discussions on StackOverflow (MSR'19) Alan Bandeira, Carlos Alberto Medeiros, Matheus Paixao, Paulo Henrique Maia 2019 Working Conference on Mining Software Repositories Rebasing in Code Review Considered Harmful: A Large-scale Empirical Investigation (SCAM'19) MATHEUS PAIXAO, PAULO HENRIQUE MAIA 2019 Source Code Analysis and Manipulation An Empirical Study of Cohesion and Coupling: Balancing Optimisation and Disruption (TEVC) MATHEUS PAIXAO, MARK HARMAN, YUANYUAN ZHANG, YIJUN YU 2018 IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary Computation CROP: Linking code reviews to source code changes (MSR'18) MATHEUS PAIXAO, JENS KRINKE, DONGGYUN HAN, MARK HARMAN Working Conference on Mining Software Repositories Who's this?: developer identification using IDE event data (MSR'18) JOHN WILKIE, ZIAD AL HALABI, ALPEREN KARAOGLU, JIAFENG LIAO, GEORGE NDUNGU, CHAIYONG RAGKHITWETSAGUL, MATHEUS PAIXAO, JENS KRINKE Working Conference on Mining Software Repositories Are Developers Aware of the Architectural Impact of Their Changes? (ASE'17) MATHEUS PAIXAO, JENS KRINKE, DONGGYUN HAN, CHAIYONG RAGKHITWETSAGUL, MARK HARMAN 2017 The 32nd IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering An architecture based on interactive optimization and machine learning applied to the next release problem (ASE Journal) ALLYSSON ALLEX ARAÚJO, MATHEUS PAIXAO, ITALO YELTSIN, ALTINO DANTAS, JERFFESON SOUZA 2017

Automated Software Engineering

## A Hyper-heuristic for Multi-objective Integration and Test Ordering in Google Guava (SSBSE'17) GIOVANI GUIZZO, MOSAB BAZARGANI, MATHEUS PAIXAO, JOHN H DRAKE 2017 International Symposium on Search Based Software Engineering Searching for configurations in clone evaluation-a replication study (SSBSE'16) Chaiyong Ragkhitwetsagul, Matheus Paixao, Manal Adham, Saheed Busari, Jens Krinke, John H Drake 2016 International Symposium on Search Based Software Engineering A robust optimization approach to the next release problem in the presence of uncertainties (JSS) MATHEUS PAIXAO, JERFFESON SOUZA 2015 Journal of Systems and Software Multi-objective module clustering for kate (SSBSE'15) MATHEUS PAIXAO, MARK HARMAN, YUANYUAN ZHANG International Symposium on Search Based Software Engineering Machine learning for user modeling in an interactive genetic algorithm for the next release problem (SSBSE'14) ALLYSSON ALLEX ARAÚJO, MATHEUS PAIXAO 2014 International Symposium on Search Based Software Engineering A mapping study of the Brazilian SBSE community (JSERD) Wesley KG Assunção, Márcio de O Barros, Thelma E Colanzi, Arilo C Dias-Neto, Matheus Paixao, Jerffeson T de 2014 Souza, Silvia R Vergilio Journal of Software Engineering Research and Development A scenario-based robust model for the next release problem (GECCO'13, Invited for Journal Extension) MATHEUS PAIXAO, JERFFESON SOUZA 2013

Annual conference on Genetic and Evolutionary Computation

International Symposium on Search Based Software Engineering

MATHEUS PAIXAO, JERFFESON SOUZA

A recoverable robust approach for the next release problem (SSBSE'13)

2013